A Guide to the Richard Harding Davis Letters Concerning South Africa and the Boer War
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Richard Harding Davis Collection, Clifton Waller Barrett Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
6109-y
The collection consists of ca. 40 items.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
These letters were given to the University of Virginia Special Collections Library by E. Anthony Newton, on July 7, 2009.
Biographical/Historical Information
Davis was born on April 18, 1864, in Philadelphia, Pennsylvania to Lemuel Clarke Davis, a newspaper editor, and prominent novelist, Rebecca Harding Davis. He made his reputation as a newspaper reporter in May to June 1889, by reporting on the devastation of Johnstown, Pennsylvania, following the disaster of the flood. Davis became a managing editor of Harper's Weekly, and was one of the world's leading war correspondents at the time of the Second Boer War in South Africa. As an American, he had the unique opportunity to see the war first-hand from both the British and Boer sides. Davis also worked as a reporter for the New York Herald, The Times, and Scribner's Magazine. He was married twice, first to Cecil Clark Lewis, an artist, in Marion, Massachusetts, on May 4, 1899, and then to Bessie McCoy, a Vaudeville star. He and Bessie had a daughter, Hope. Davis died of a heart attack at home on April 11, 1916 at fifty-one years of age. Several books were consulted for information concerning Davis and his trip to South Africa, including The Richard Harding David Years by Gerald Langford, The Reporter Who Would Be King by Arthur Lubow and With Both Armies by Richard Harding Davis.
Scope and Content
This collection contains Richard Harding Davis Letters concerning South Africa and the Boer War. Letters and documents by Richard Harding Davis and his wife Cecil describe their voyages to and from South Africa, the cities of Cape Town and Pretoria, and his coverage of the Boer War from both the British and the Boer sides. There are references to General Buller, Winston Churchill, Lady Randolph Churchill, Christiaan de Wet, Rudyard Kipling, Paul Kruger, Sir Alfred Milner, Lord Frederick Roberts, Allen Sangree, President M. T. Steyn, and Sir George Stuart White. Of great interest are letters describing the relief of Ladysmith, March 3-4, 1900, and the fall of Pretoria, May 18, 1900. A photograph of Cecil in a rickshaw in Durban is included as is a magazine of their return ship the R. P. D. König of the Deutsche Ost-Afrika-Linie.
These letters were formerly mounted into a scrapbook and numbered consecutively with a penciled notation at the top of the letter. The letters have been removed from the scrapbook for preservation purposes. The collection is now arranged by the date of the letter, or if undated, by the contents of the letter, and not the original order as arranged in the scrapbook, presumably that of the date of receipt.
Item number 10 is actually two separate letters on two consecutive days, so it has been foldered separately. Several numbers, 25, 28, 30, and 32, are missing and those items are presumed lost or mis-numbered by the recipient or the creator of the scrapbook. There are also two items numbered 33. When it can be determined, the entire name of the correspondent is used in the listing, even if the letter has only the first name or a nickname. This is indicated by the use of brackets.
Contents List
- [1900 January 10?] Cecil [Clark Davis] to Dear Mrs. [Rebecca Harding] Davis, note on U.S.M.S. St. Louis stationery, saying goodbye to the Davis family, including Mr. Davis and Nora Davis, as they are sailing to London to secure authorization for Richard to cover the Boer War with the British forces in the Transvaal, 1 page on 1 leaf (Box-folder 1:1)
- [1900 January] 10-13 Richard Harding Davis ("Dick") to Dear Mother [Rebecca Harding Davis], written on U.S.M.S. St. Louis stationery, states he and his wife, Cecil, have the most comfortable staterooms, they have met many people who claim to have met them before, everyone is very interested in their trip, and travel was very smooth until Saturday, 4 pages on 1 leaf (Box-folder 1:2)
- [1900 January 13] [Richard Harding Davis] to [Rebecca Harding Davis?], written on U.S.M.S. St. Louis stationery, Saturday, sea continues to be stormy, tells a story about a man at his table who put up a freight trolley line over the Chilkoot Pass to the Klondike district in the Yukon Territory, Canada, and used it to ferry sixty frozen bodies over it in buckets at one time; their ship is halfway across to Great Britain; they also had tea with the Cass Canfield couple and talked politics at dinnertime. The Klondike man claims he is a great leader in the Democratic party and predicts they will toss out Bryan at the Convention at the last minute and nominate Dewey or Olney with Wheeler as vice president. He assures them that this is the strategy of Whitney and Josiah Quincy., 4 pages on 1 leaf (Box-folder 1:3)
- [1900 January 20?] [Richard Harding Davis] to Dear Nora [Davis], Bath Hotel, arrived on Wednesday at two in the morning at the hotel and the porter brought them food and drink as they sat in front of the fire; could not leave on Saturday because the War Office refused him credentials; if they still refuse to issue them, Davis plans on going without them, using instead letters of introduction from [Herbert?] Asquith and others, to [Frederick] Roberts, Lord [Alfred?] Milner, and [Herbert] Kitchener. They missed traveling down [to the Transvaal] with [Rudyard] Kipling but on next Saturday plan to go with [Henry Somers] Somerset, who cannot get a job as a correspondent. Cecil has letters from Mrs. Asquith to Lady Edward Cecil and Lady Charles Benedict, both of whom are at Mafeking., 4 pages on 1 leaf (Box-folder 1:4)
- [1900 January 22?] Richard [Harding Davis] to Dear Nora [Davis], on Bath Hotel, Piccadilly, stationery, tries to relate all the exciting things that have happened since they have arrived in [London?] because their situation seems to change by the hour, trying to decide whether to go with the British or the Boers, to stay in London or return home, to work for The Herald or The Mail; The British refused to give Davis a correspondent pass and he had decided to go with the Boers, when [George W.] Steevens died and Lord Alfred Harmsworth asked him if he could break with The Herald and take Steevens place. He offered to write for both papers, which [James Gordon] Bennett, Jr. finally agreed to. Richard and Cecil also have had dinner with Mrs. [Herbert?] Asquith; at another dinner, Cecil sat next to [Alfred] Beit, who gave them letters to "all the millionaire Hebrews at the Cape, wives and all. He is the man who subscribed $250,000 for the volunteers and who is described as the man who paid for the Jameson Raid. He paid [John Hays] Hammond's fine which was in itself $175,000.", 7 pages on 2 leaves (Box-folder 1:5)
- [1900 January 23?] Cecil [Clark Davis] to Mrs. [Rebecca Harding] Davis, Tuesday, writes "We are leading such a busy life these days & meeting so many new & exciting people that my brain reels - At last things are fixed about the credentials. Dick is to take the place of Steevens & write for The Daily Mail." Taking over Steevens credentials were arranged with the help of Sir Evelyn Wood. Cecil also mentions the help given them by Alfred Beit who furnished letters of introduction and arranged rooms for them in South Africa through his partners. Davis's play was well received by Cyril Maude who wanted to show it to Wyndham. Richard's sciatica has also improved. Cecil mentioned needing a maid to go to South Africa and the rumors about the food shortages there., 3 pages on 1 leaf (Box-folder 1:6)
- [1900 January 27?] [Richard Harding Davis] to "Dear Mother" [Rebecca Harding Davis] on Steamship S.S. Scot stationery, Davis is on board and leaving port, has bribed the company agent to get Cecil and himself better staterooms, with Cecil's large enough to give teas and dances, also rescuing their maid with a room of her own and saving himself a considerable amount of money by dealing with the agent instead of the company. Many friends came to see them off and they are accompanied by [Henry Somers] Somerset and Butler Duncan of New York. He asks his mother to tell Louise Clark what he has written and give his love to Nora and Dad., 4 pages on 1 leaf (Box-folder 1:7)
- [1900] January 31 [Richard Harding Davis] to Nora [Davis], on Steamship S.S. Scot stationery, reports that the trip has been rough so far, making them glad to see land, even if it is only a slice of Portugal; Davis plans to try to go with Kitchener, the main column, and will not try to pick up the ends of the other campaigns; feels that since Kitchener cannot start for several weeks, he will have plenty of time to settle Cecil in Cape Town, South Africa, with friends and her maid, "I think her chance of getting to the front is extremely small - extremely so - what we both want is a quick campaign lots of things to write about and a quick return - with The Mail and The Herald I now have a great chance and an immense audience, and nothing is read in England except war letters." Both Richard and Cecil were very happy at the Bath [Hotel] in London, and Cecil now loves the city as much as he does. Notes that they did not receive any of his mother's letters while in London., 7 pages on 2 leaves (Box-folder 1:8)
- [1900] January 31 Cecil [Clark Davis] to Mrs. [Rebecca Harding] Davis, on Steamship S.S. Scot stationery, off Madeira, complains that "Dick tells you everything & leaves me nothing; which is perhaps as well as he is certainly a good describer"; mentions the rough seas, the possibility of a casino and roulette table night to relieve the monotony on board, hearing much of Transvaal matters, especially inside stories from [Alfred] Beit; she writes "am in the painful state of being half convinced that the English have rights - However I think I can escape all troubles by turning Kaffir & Red American Indians & [Filipino] & from this high moral stand no one can move me"; she also notes that she is supposed to "sustain the wounded" when she arrives in Cape Town., 3 pages on 1 leaf (Box-folder 1:9)
- [1900] February 4 "Dick" Richard [Harding Davis] to "Dear Mother" [Rebecca Harding Davis], describes in great detail the adventures they had on the trip by Portuguese rowboat to Madeira taken by himself, Cecil, and Somers, in very rough and high seas, his success at the roulette table the brief while they were in the casino, the order of champagne for everyone out of his winnings, leaving him seventy-five dollars to the good, his meal of fried eggs, and the negotiation for payment on the return trip., 5 pages on 3 leaves (Box-folder 1:10)
- 1900 February 9 "Dick" [Richard Harding Davis] to "Dear Mother" [Rebecca Harding Davis] on Steamship S.S. Scot stationery, describes their participation in the "sports" contests on board ship through Cecil's maid, Hubert, who won the threading a needle contest; the reassurance by people who have lived in Cape Town for awhile that they have introductory letters to the most important people there, including almost every multimillionaire out of Kimberly, [Lord Alfred] Milner, and the ladies nursing the wounded, so Richard has no uneasiness about leaving Cecil in their care while he hopes to make his way to the front with either Roberts or Kitchener. He believes the war an immense opportunity, "as all the officers say, it is like taking a degree in war there will not be such a chance again, and there has never been one like it - I mean the use of modern weapons has been developed in the campaign for the first time.", 4 pages on 1 leaf (Box-folder 1:11)
- 1900 February [10] "Dick" [Richard Harding Davis] to "Dear Mother" [Rebecca Harding Davis] on Steamship S.S. Scot stationery, describes the very English manner of awarding the prizes for the sports contest held yesterday involving a great deal of pomp and circumstance. Their maid, Hubert, gave her prize money to the two youngest cabin boys., 4 pages on 1 leaf (Box-folder 1:12)
- [1900] February 14 "Dick" [Richard Harding Davis] to "Dear Mother" [Rebecca Harding Davis], on Mount Nelson Hotel, Cape Town, stationery, writes that they are settled in a very smart hotel with many gardens and facing the mountains "owing to the crowding Somerset has to room with me - Cecil has a very good room by herself"; [H.J.] Whigham has quarreled with [Paul Sanford Baron] Methuen and lost his press pass to the front; and Richard mentions Rudyard Kipling, "Kipling is at the hotel and walks around with his arm around his wife's waist - He is very friendly, she is a middle class cat.", 3 pages on 3 leaves (Box-folder 1:13)
- 1900 February 17 Telegram from [Richard Harding Davis] notifying his [family ?] that Cecil was settled and that he was going to Chieveley with General Sir Redvers Buller (Box-folder 1:14)
- [1900] February 18-19 "Dick" [Richard Harding Davis] to "Dear Mother" [Rebecca Harding Davis], on board Scot, Richard left [Cape Town] yesterday and hopes to reach Buller before Ladysmith is relieved and possibly join Roberts with Buller later; plans to do a lot of cabling for the Mail every day; describes Cape Town as a "dusty wind-ridden western town with a mountain back of it which one man said was a badly painted back drop"; Cecil is settled in a hotel situated at the base of the mountain with a sitting room and a big bedroom; they have met [Sir Alfred] Milner, who volunteered to write an unsolicited and flattering personal letter of introduction to the Governor of Natal for Richard; describes his discussion with Milner about his doubts of the loyalty of the Cape Towners to the Queen; Cecil has become friends with the Waldrons and Mrs. Anderson, but dislikes the Kiplings, "She hates the Kiplings as everyone does, a more offensive little bounder it is difficult to imagine - He goes around in khaki 800 miles from the front and contradicts every general on every military question - He ought either to go the front or go home"; Richard has boarded ship [S.S. Scot] and parted from Cecil, describes their preparations for his voyage to join Buller and his arrangements to cable his stories to the Mail, and plans to post this letter at Port Elizabeth, 8 pages on 4 leaves (Box-folder 1:15)
- [1900] February 19 "Dick" [Richard Harding Davis] to "Dear Mother" [Rebecca Harding Davis], on Bunton's Grand Hotel, Port Elizabeth, stationery, Richard is currently on shore at Port Elizabeth, describes the local scene with rickshaws drawn by Kaffir boys, the town looking like a western mining town, strange looking ducks that turned out to be baby ostriches, and the vast distances of Africa where it will still take him ten days to reach Buller's location, 2 pages on 1 leaf (Box-folder 1:16)
- [1900] February 20 "Dick" [Richard Harding Davis] to "Dear dear Mother" [Rebecca Harding Davis], on Deal's Central Hotel stationery, East London, South Africa, writes that the Scot is stopping at every port as if it were a ferry boat; has met an American who got a commission in Brabant's Horse and who had the hotel proprietor bring out two books to sign marked "Autographs of Celebrities of the Boer War" for Davis to autograph; and notes that many of the correspondents are now abandoning Buller for Roberts, 2 pages on 2 leaves (Box-folder 1:17)
- [1900] February 20 Cecil [Clark Davis] to Mrs. [Rebecca Harding] Davis, mistaken dated "1899" by Cecil, on Mount Nelson Hotel, Cape Town, stationery, writes that Richard left yesterday on the Scot to go to Durban and then on to Pietermaritzsburg for his horses and cart to join Buller at the Tugela [River], a journey of a week by sea and then three to four more days by land; seems like the war is much further away than when she was in England with less news about it; she is not impressed with Cape Town which she thinks is something between a frontier town and Cairo and Algiers; Somerset and Whigham sit at her table at the hotel and she sees the Kiplings in the dining room to her dismay, 6 pages on 3 leaves (Box-folder 1:18)
- [1900] February 23 "Dick" [Richard Harding Davis] to "Dear Mother" [Rebecca Harding Davis], on Imperial Hotel, Maritzburg, Natal, stationery, writes that he reached Durban yesterday and describes it as picturesque with many different nationalities; plans to overtake Buller before he reaches Ladysmith; and describes the native peoples he has seen, 3 pages on 2 leaves, with a broadside dated February 21, 1900, Supplement to the Cape Times "Good News From Buller" enclosed, 3 pages on 2 leaves (Box-folder 1:19)
- [1900] March 1 "Dick" [Richard Harding Davis] to "Dear Kid" [Charles Belmont Davis], mistakenly dated 1899, sends notification of his arrival in Ladysmith with postmarked envelope [dated March 1, 1900] as proof, "This is just a line to say I got in here with the first after a gallop of twelve miles. Keep this for me and the envelope, with my love and best wishes - Dick", 1 page (Box-folder 1:20)
- [1900] March 1 Cecil [Clark Davis] to Mrs. [Rebecca Harding] Davis, Mount Nelson Hotel, Cape Town, stationery, has received a telegram from Richard at Colenso and has also heard that Piet Cronje has surrendered [at Paardeberg?]; she has made some drawings but found far fewer subjects than expected, an entire Kaffir family watched as she drew the grandmother in her room; Kipling has returned from Kimberley; and she expects to meet Cecil Rhodes soon, 3 pages on 1 leaf (Box-folder 1:21)
- [1900 March 2?] "Dick" [Richard Harding Davis] to "Dear dear Mother" [Rebecca Harding Davis], boasts that on his second day "I beat all these men who have been here three months in getting my news on the wire. For I am a news man now and have to collect horrid facts and lists of casualties and to find out whether it was the Dublins or the Durbans that did it and what it was they did." The geography of the area around the Tugela River is confusing; Richard claims that he is as comfortable in his tent as can be, which he describes as well as his three ponies; and he speaks of heavy losses, "it is sheer straight waste of life through dogged stupidity", 4 pages on 2 leaves (Box-folder 1:22)
- [1900] March 3-4 "Dick" [Richard Harding Davis] to "Dear Mother" [Rebecca Harding Davis], Ladysmith, March 3, Davis describes the relief of Ladysmith by Sir Redvers Buller's soldiers, who form quite a contrast with the poor conditions of health of the garrison, "They are yellow with fever, their teeth protruding and the skin drawn tight over their skeletons - the incoming army had had fourteen days hard fighting at the end of three months campaigning and were robust and tanned ragged and caked with mud. As they came in they cheered and the garrison tried to cheer back but it was like a whisper - Winston Churchill and I stood in front of General [Sir George] White and cried for an hour." Davis also mentions the heavy losses among the men trying to break the siege, the scarcity of food, his ration of four biscuits, an ounce of coffee and of tea, along with something called mealies., 5 pages on 3 leaves (Box-folder 1:23)
  Ladysmith, March 4, has received the first letter from her since they left home, complains about how the British have fought the war, "It is a beastly dull war - the whole thing is so 'class', and full of 'form' and tradition and worrying over 'putties' and etiquette and rank - It is the most wonderful organization I ever imagined but it is like a beautiful locomotive without an engineer - the Boers out play them in intelligence every day - the whole army is officered by one class and that the dull one - It is like the House of Peers - You would not believe the mistakes they make, the awful way in which they sacrifice the lives of officers and men." Both portions,
- [1900] March 5 "Dick" [Richard Harding Davis] to "Dear Mother" [Rebecca Harding Davis], Outside Ladysmith, Davis complains about the filth, smell, and dirt of the town and his hotel and the attitude of the familiarity of the "colonials"; tells a story of several very hungry troopers who came into the dining room to purchase some tea who were refused rudely; he followed them out and begged them to take tea with him on his verandah and served them the scarce commodities of sugar, marmalade, whiskey, and cigars that he had purchased; also saved a small puppy which he fed on beef tablets and named Ladysmith; describes his beautiful tent with tape window panes, ventilators, pockets inside, doors, two tables, two chairs, a bath tub, two lanterns, folding bed, and a cape cart; and tells a sad story about the men of Ladysmith driving away well-trained cavalry horses because they could not be fed., 6 pages on 3 leaves (Box-folder 1:24)
- [1900] March 15 "Dick" [Richard Harding Davis] to "Dear Mother" [Rebecca Harding Davis], on Royal Hotel, Durban, Natal, stationery, returning to Cape Town, Davis plans to go to Roberts if there is fighting or return to London if there is not; takes issue with the British fighting against women "even if they are good shots"; has not seen enough to make a book out of his trip and both he and Cecil have been bored with all the talk about the war; traveled to the hospital ship The Maine and asked Lady Randolph [Spencer Churchill] to give him a lift down to Cape Town and plans on writing an article for her Anglo-Saxon Review on the "Passing of the War Correspondent.", 7 pages on 2 leaves (Box-folder 1:25)
- 1900 March 24 Telegram from L. Clarke Davis to Mrs. L. Clarke Davis, received a message from Richard Harding Davis, "seen enough war returning next week east coast very leisurely", 1 page (Box-folder 1:26)
- [1900] March 25 "Dick" [Richard Harding Davis] to [the Clark and Davis families?], Cape Town, writes explaining his decision to return home, both Roberts and Buller planned on no campaigning for about three weeks and he had already sold his outfit at a loss; since the English irritated him he could not write about their work with any pleasure, "My sporting blood refused to boil at the spectacle of such a monster empire getting the worst of it from an untrained band of farmers - I found I admired the farmers - so we decided to chuck it and go to London." Davis had seen two battles and the relief of Ladysmith, having gotten the "pick of the fighting and the best 'story' according to every officer and correspondent; they intend on returning home via the east coast [of Africa?] so Cecil can enjoy some of the "real Africa not the shoddy 'colonial', shopkeeper's paradise" as in Cape Town; Richard and Cecil Davis plan on stopping off at Zanzibar, Port Said, Cairo, Constantinople, and then on to Paris by way of the Orient Express, perhaps writing a book about the entire experience with photographs and Cecil's drawings; he encloses a printed itinerary that they will follow when they board the Konig, at Durban, leaving April 7 th; and explains why he thinks Cecil's maid, Hubert, is a priceless treasure., 5 pages on 3 leaves (Box-folder 1:27)
- [1900] March 31 "Dick" [Richard Harding Davis] to "Dear Mother" [Rebecca Harding Davis], off East Africa, his joy at turning towards home together with Cecil and his appreciation of her letters and enclosures about events at home, 2 pages on 1 leaf (Box-folder 1:28)